So I’d like to thank Jason for inviting me.
I have to say I feel
woefully unprepared
all the stuff I’ve been listening to, you pretty
much have to be a kernel developer here
it's not even enough to be like a normal committer I imagine
um you have to have invented something really cool
I'm here as a user
to try to take the loser off of it
I didn’t even boot into the BSD side of my laptop so
no rocks thrown up here
I wanted to talk about actually
how many people here had some kind of security responsibility
okay so wow that’s interesting
okay so there are a lot of security people here
I usually speak to security audiences
when I speak in
or when I spoke before at
BSD conferences it was usually on something
something I was doing with BSD
for security purposes so I kind of
had that same theme for today
so what we’ll talk about
just so you know I am I worked in a variety
of
I was in the military where I learned all this stuff
I work in commercial industry defense contractors
I worked for a small start up
out of Connecticut
you might have heard of us
we’ve lost like three hundred billion in market cap over
the last year it’s been an exciting ride
the ads General Electric we get three hundred thousand users
um just a few security issues as you might
imagine
company that size
but what I’m going to talk about
uh first of all I’ll just do sort of a
intro of how I think about security
and why it drived me down the road of having
devices that I’ll talk about
and I’ll
I’m open to any questions it’s funny I was actually sitting
in front of a couple of guys who were asking me
we were talking about
that some of the software I’ll talk about he didn’t even
realize it was me
sitting at front
so if any point you have questions about
how we do things why we do things
please let me know
what I’m going to describe isn’t exactly what I do
with General Electric
or at least it's not officially what I do at General
Electric
but you can imagine that I just don’t come up with
this stuff in a vacuum and then present it obviously
it's
based on what I think works in various environments
so my job title is director of incident response
and what I tell people that they usually think of
oil spills or
you know Hazmat or something like that
its information security incidents
and I like to say that I’m as close to the problem
as you possibly could be
right and we have project managers who are
trying to create risk equations
they're trying to figure out if I tweak this
knob it’ll result in more risk or less risk
I think that’s a whole bunch of
crap for the most part
%um
I deal with all the failures so I
deal with failure all around
I like to say that this
theory out there but the reality is when
okay you've got
dozens or hundreds or thousands of systems
that are compromised what do you do about that
so in some ways you might say that's actually
the worst possible place to do security is after it’s
failed but
in other ways maybe it's the best place because
you can see what's wrong and you can try to fix it
well you have to say what is security and I went
to the doctor one day and the doctor asked me questions
like well how do you feel
do you feel healthy
that's kind of like do you feel secure
so what is that even mean right I mean
if you think about health well you might say
how’s your blood pressure
well it’s under 120 over 80
that's sort of one data point
what about your cholesterol body mass index and so forth
the idea is that you have to measure something
and you have to get your data from somewhere
and what I find is that a lot of people who make
security decisions
are not getting data from anywhere
In fact
a lot of very high level security people
are getting data on the golf course when they're
talking to their fellow
CSIO’s about
hey what product are you buying from Cisco or this and that
and it’s completely disconnected from reality
and as a result nobody can tell whether they’re spending
any money on security that makes a difference
%um or how to get
how to get better
so like how many people here are sort of like involved in
federal security with like FISMA and stuff
like that that right
so I find all that to be the most frustrating thing possible
I don't deal with that because I’m in private industry
but I've commented on it quite a bit because I
have a blog
and I like to complain
so my feeling is that the FISMA folks
not be implement but the people who wrote the legislation
they tended
to focus on things like imput metrics
like do you have AV
do you have your patches
is the box configured properly
all those things of that nature
I call all those input metrics they really make no difference
as far as I'm concerned if you're truly trying to figure
out what the problem is
it's kind of like looking at a
sports teams let’s say an American football team
and you say well
input metrics would be like how tall are all the players
how fast do they run the forty
where did they go to school
you could look at all those things
but does that tell you what their
what their record was over the season
did they win the Super Bowl did they win their elite
championship
no those are those are all inputs right
I care about ouputs like
is this box is this box part of a bot net
no it’s not really Windows
%um
I could boot it into Windows but
I prefer to stay out of the bot net
did you
have an earnings report appear on the network share or
on a peer-to-peer network somewhere
that's an ouput that means you had a failure somewhere
do you have a system or network that’s unavailable
due to a DDoS attack
these are all outputs so
I try to focus on these
I really don't care so much about that I think
these can influence these
these are the things that I care about
and just to step a
little bit out and change the way you might think
about this there was a good article in The Economist last
year where they talked about people who are
trying to make
policy decisions
about health policy in Africa
and it's a safe thing with security
right actually kind of what I like about seeing the
developers here is that in the last talk there was
lots of discussions about
you made this change and you get a 5% difference
or you made this change and you get a 10% difference
none of that happens in security
it's all well we’ll deploy this and see what happens
actually it’s not even that we’ll deploy this
not even let's see what happens
there’s not even a test to see if it made any difference
so what I try to
focus on in my job
at GE is
let's do some tests like
the company is big enough
why don't we have part of the company
run
with no local admin on the desktop
and another part
continuing to run its local admin I didn’t say that
out loud sorry
and then compare and see what the infection rates are
and guess what I bet the ones with local admin
are going to be a hell of a lot worse
and there’s been some recent studies that have
shown that that's the case
so you can run these sort of policy-based trials
and figure out what you should do
then I can go talk to my boss and be like look
this part of the company that runs with local admin
they’re ten times worse than everybody else
and even better I can say it's costing us ten
times more
then we can make a change
but in order to do that you have to have
some kind of measurements
you’re going to have data come from somewhere
and I like to say that I call this management
by fact not by belief
the there's a lot like
security people are very religious
we have this
idea of what should be and what shouldn’t be
and it's all because we don't think usually
measure what works which is unfortunate
so I’m all about visibility I want to find out what's
going on
and the reason I think about it this way is
I think in the air force
we have this thing called OODA loop
and if you’ve ever seen my hands doing this it’s because
I'm reliving my air force days flying around in my F-16
not really I only flew once in the F-16 and
once in the F-15
but
when I would talk to the fighter pilots they would talk
about having this thing the OODA loop
and it came out
like I’m thinking before the first gulf war
and the idea was you’re in your
F-16
and you want to win the fight so
the first thing you do is look out the window
you see what's going on
that's your observation
and then you orient and you figure out well where am
I in relation to where the bad guys are
then you make a decision like okay there’s a bad guy
I better roll over and shoot it down
and then you take the action
the problem we have with security
is that
there's none of this
there’s no observe and orient
there’s only decide and act
so we have no idea what's happening
but we're told that to do things so we buy stuff
we deploy it
and we just keep doing that over and over again
and we never figure out if it makes any difference
the unfortunate thing is if you do
stumble upon something that works it's
usually luck
%uh as opposed to
figuring it out by observation and orientation
what you should be doing
so this is probably my favorite description
of security period
my apologies to my European friends this
is the football poll security
but this is what I believe that I've seen
this just for years and years and years
the idea is you’re told
or you read in a magazine
or you talk to your buddy
about something bad
and you assume that that bad thing that's
happening it must be happening at your location
too
and sometimes it is but sometimes it isn’t
and so you run around and you spend all this time
on one area
while meanwhile you could be completely all about
something different
and I first started thinking about this in 2000-2001
where there were some guys in Finland
who did this huge enumeration they were doing some of the
first fuzzing work against SMTP
it was called
The Protos Toolkit
and they did all this work in and they found that
basically everybody's SMTP
implementation was really bad
and they were all vulnerable
and the whole world was going to end because
SMTP vulnerabilities existed everywhere
well I don’t know if everybody was around back then
so they're looking at these things
but did the world end in 2001
with SMTP
absolutely not
so while a lot of effort was spent on
spending all this time fixing SMTP implementations
when the bad guys really weren’t
taking advantage of it
so this is what I feel like is happening with
security now we're told about
this is the one that really kills me is
insider threats
oh they’re insider threats they're so bad
this in that and so you spend all your time over
here and you’re like
paying attention to your own employees you’re violating
their rights and their privacy
and meanwhile you got like
Romanians and Russians and Chinese and
every other
hacker in the world inside your company
that you can't do anything about
unless you know unless you actually do something
so my goal is to
get it so this guy he's looking at the right
spot
so at least he has a chance
right he doesn’t even have a chance if he’s looking
over there at least if you can sort of
orient and say okay well here’s this threat
here's what I need to do about it
you have a chance you still might get scored on right
but at least you can say
I had a fighting chance many organizations
when I was a consultant
I would drop into
and they didn't even have a fighting chance
there was just no
I would call them you know indefensible networks
to use a Cisco term I would call them self-defeating networks
self-defending anyway
yeah
the network part of ours sure
so yeah isn’t it interesting the self-defending network what
does that imply zero head count
that is the truth behind Cisco's vision
and think about it they sell it to every CIO
the CIO is like yeah
the network takes care of itself
oh yeah that means you you you you bye bye
and that's sort of the model that
I mean think about it
what business owner with would
not want to operate zero staff
if you could still make money
and no people
oh that's great
maybe you just have robots or something right don't they
don’t complain
So anyway wow
that came out of nowhere
but %uh
that's what I see with a lot of things is a %uh
presumption that you just buy products right you
don't actually
invest in people so
back to this whole idea of visibility the question is
well where should you try to get visibility
and I’ll talk about what kind of visibility
well the model that I use is to establish trust
boundaries first and what’s interesting about
using a trust boundary approach is
it can apply anywhere
I use a network example here because
it's a low-cost way to do it
but you can apply trust boundaries
on a system
within an application
I mean there’s lots of different places that you can apply
trust boundaries
the idea is though once you establish trust boundaries
start watching
something there
so I’m going to use a network example but you could
you know apply it someplace else
so what I do is I
the general process is I identify my trust boundaries
I apply some instrumentation
and then I collect analyze and escalate
%uh collect meaning I get the information
analyze I look at it figure out what it means
escalate
is take it to somebody who cares
surprisingly difficult to find those people
in many
enterprises
I came from the DOD where
if we found a single machine that was compromised
that was an incident
and it could be reported all the way up to some
general
who would be on the phone
like barking orders that you need to fix this
within
hours or days or whatever it was
to private industry
where
you finding a compromise computer
and the response could be
eh what can they do
well they can access any machine that’s in this domain
well have they
%uh because I just got here I can't tell yet
I really don't know if we have to care about
this right
the only thing that’s changed that recently has been the
disclosure laws
because there are some disclosure laws that say if
it's possible that they could have stolen the data
you need to report
so that's changed the equation
dramatically
right it used to be in fact I worked some big
cases years ago where it was like
well you guys signed an NDA with us right yeah we
did
right well just bye bye
see you later
okay great alright well I’m glad I’m not a customer
at this place
I didn’t responded there I bank with Bank of America and the
reason I bank with Bank of America
is I know the guy who runs security there
and he does this
so of course
I still think he has a job
now that I think about it
has he been replaced by a robot
no he hasn’t been replaced by a robot
maybe his minions have been replaced by
Perl strips but
he’s still there
so this is my general process
and it’s funny people have probably heard about building security in
that's like trying to make things more secure
have been trying to do that for like 20 years
it just doesn't work
so I would say let’s monitor first because at least when you monitor you can tell that something bad is happening
if you just say build security in and walk away
then you’re in trouble
what I find is that in any product you have
this cycle
where you start out with a feature
and then the features proliferate and you need to manage them
and then somebody’s like oh yeah we need to apply
some security to that
and then finally check to see if it works when really
it should be the other way
figure out what’s out there
build a security policy for it
manage it
and then introduce the feature but that's
not how it’s done
I wanted to mention here some I just want
to put this on the table before I go into my
next part because these are they
%uh criticisms I usually hear
so let's just mention them now so if I’m taking some kind of
a network-centric approach to
security
the first thing we’re always told is well what about the
cloud
and this is very interesting %uh I work really
closely with the guy does the cloudsecurity.org
blog
and %uh he's a fellow employee with
me is that we always considering this because
we’re
putting more and more of our stuff in the cloud
and if your
window to the cloud
is an SSL encrypted pipe
%um it doesn't help me too much to inspect it at the
network level right
so we're going to have to push our cloud vendors
to provide the visibility for us
oh boy that’s really happening
try getting good logs out of any of the cloud buyers
it is absolutely horrible they don't
want to store them they don't want
to provide you the data in any format that’s useful
if they provide you with anything it's generally
performance metrics like
we cleaned ten billion of your emails today
oh that’s wonderful that’s great you know I don’t care
I don’t care how many emails you cleaned
I want to know about
which ones came from this
%uh a person who
was phishing us
and you know got control of some of our systems and
so forth
virtualization is obviously an issue
%um if you think about
in a one-machine
one
platform world
any time two machines talk you can potentially see the
traffic
what happens when you have a hundred machines all on one
platform
unless you instrument the virtual machine
itself
you know one hundred machines could all be infected an
talking to each other and stuff but
the way I deal with that is
unless the bad guy is also inside the VM
like he lives in it
you can see him because generally the people
you care about are on another continent
so
I mean it could be
somewhere else in the United States obviously but for
the most part like if someone were to compromise
my machine
unless they physically walk up to it and touch it
there will be some network traffic that reaches out
and generally that’s enough
to tell that there’s a problem
so maybe the fastest way to tell if there’s a
kernel rootkit on a system
it’s for the system to look normal
but to have it to be beaconing out to
you know take your pick of rogue country
so that that's a very effective way to
use to find stuff
And of course you’ve got your non-traditional
platforms
you know I’ve got my Blackberry here I absolutely love it
but I would love to be able sniff the traffic
going to and from it
because
who knows who’s sitting on my Blackberry right now
I really don't know
and that kills me
it kills me kills me kills me
that I cannot
find an interface sniff traffic on it and see
what's happening
or somehow get between the wireless
watch the traffic and see what's happening
so that to me it's a big issue
and we’ve got all these crazy European privacy laws
I can’t collect anything in that whole continent
not true it kills me though it's kind of difficult
%um you’ve got this tension between
%uh it's interesting Europeans tend to have very
strong collection laws like you have to keep logs for a
certain period of time
but at the same time they have very strong privacy laws
so this is a tension there
skilled resources I don't know about you but
it
even with the downturn it's tough to find
good security people I think
there's a lot of people who come out with
their Cisco certified
whatever
and they don't know the first thing about
how to actually secure anything which is tough
and then finally we see this quite often in software
security space
a lot of the tools that are out there were
built for
developers
and for performance and not for security
So you see people using tools
to disassemble malware that were built
for reverse engineering for software purposes
and not for security purposes
anyway so what I’m going to talk about briefly
is not new
I was actually cleaning out
an old drive and I found this presentation
from 2000
I used to give this briefing when I was in
the air force cert
and we would talk about the history of our
unit
and back in 1993
we were deploying what we call network security
monitoring systems
and
the NSN term
comes from
the first network based IDS that taught
he wrote it in UC Davis in 1989
so this is wow that’s 20 years I feel
freaking old right now
it’s amazing
so
so this is not a new thing and I wrote a book about this
in 2004 so
that's five years
ago now so
this is not new the funny thing is vendors
is finally start to catch up with it
and they call them network forensic appliances
and they charge you 50,000 dollars
for the enterprise that’s right
yeah enterprise means expensive
I like that
that’s good
and GUI that's right
and somebody you can complain to who can’t really answer
your problems
alright so I present this because I don’t want to take credit
for this approach
because
people we were doing this I came in around here
but we were doing this earlier
so I learned from people who invented this stuff
you know wow that's like 15 years ago
alright so why network censors
I have to say some of the artwork I saw in these
presentations were so awesome I feel that mine’s
terrible I mean it was
the lego stuff that was great I need to do like a
little lego pyramid
I really like that but this is different
I wondered where you got your bricks from I have to like
raid my kids lego
that is funny that is good though I’m a visual
I was right in there with the bricks
so
I call this my top security enterprise trust pyramid
I ripped this out of something I used to do when
I was a consultant
and basically it’s a justification for why it’s good to have
network censors and the idea is this
this is the least trusted part and this is the most trusted
that's low user interaction and this is high user interaction
and this also in terms of the numbers of devices
so in an enterprise you tend to have the most
user platforms
desktops laptops phones all that kind of stuff
above that you have servers
above that you have infrastructure
%um routers firewalls things like that and above
that you have censors
so I trust these the least
because
well because there are these
users
right and users are doing things like
interacting with the system
if they didn’t interact with the system I would
probably trust it more
but because they’re on the system
they could be running as an admin
they're going to all these
you know malicious web sites
even normal web sites
that have been owned or are injecting malicious job descripts
or whatever
so the more user interaction there is
the less likely I’m going to trust what
the system tells me
so why get on a system and I say
tell me how you're feeling you know what your
state
I'm not going to trust that system eighty
is generally worthless
you have to get outside of the this is
the key point
you have to get away from these things you
have to get outside the system to get of you
whether or not
you should trust it
but that's not the case right
we're moving more and more to pushing all the security
down to the end point
so like my laptop defends itself
my phone defends itself
guess what if they fail
the whole model fails as well
so above this we have servers I
trust servers a little bit more
because if you're a good admin
you're not surfing
MySpace on your Windows Server
right well you’re not on a Windows Server
but well you can admin on a Windows Server
but you know what I mean
well because I think that's right that's true
above that you have infrastructure
no one should be
in general
like no user is directly
dealing with a firewall
if a user is logging into a firewall
there’s a problem right
a user doesn't necessarily log into a server but he uses
services on the server right
so I tend to trust this even more
because you just can't touch them
the number of people who deal with the infrastructure in
general is smaller than the number of people who deal
with servers
and in many cases the infrastructure is completely
you know invisible
alright how many people like interact with a router when
you're sending traffic through
no you know it passes traffic
same with the firewall blocks it allows it whatever
so I tend to trust
what this will tell me even more because there's
less user action
the final stage here is my sensor
the sensors completely pass it
most of the people in the company might not even know it
exists
which is which is good in most cases
unless you want a deterrent effect
so I can get data from the sensor
typically like in my team
there's only two people that even know the route
password
we could heavily defend these things
we can have them defend
each other
like watch each other
so I tend to have a very very high confidence to
what the sensor is telling me
as opposed to
what a user platform is telling me
so
if I’m on a user platform
and I'm looking around for evidence of a rootkit
and I see nothing
but up here in my sensor showing traffic going by
out to some site in Brazil
then I can say
alright we have a problem here
so this is why I like
to introduce these sorts of devices
let me talk a little bit
to about
least trusted and most trusted
if you had to rank operating systems here
would you put Windows up here
and BSD here
or the other way around right
so I like to use BSD especially for my sensors
because I introduce what we call a technology gap
my company we use a lot of Windows as you
might imagine
and we use a lot of Linux
we don't use a lot of BSD in fact I’m
probably the only BSD
shop in the company that I know of
but that's good
because if you’re a bad guy and you get inside the company
and you root our Windows infrastructure and you root our
Linux infrastructure
and then you find some BSD boxes
and we administer them ourselves
it's going to take a lot more work to get
into this
and we’re probably did notice when you're trying
to get into our systems
so it does not make sense and I’ve seen
we get a lot of pressure on this internally
and I’ve seen it in other companies
to have our sensing
infrastructure
be integrated with the rest of the company
right oh just have you know
have our hosted Linux service
where you know you can have
potentially all these admins you don't know
on another continent logging into your devices
no way you know I want a gap I want
the stuff that we have to protect
not be
the same as what’s using
or not be
the same systems that we’re using to watch this
so I introduced BSD as
as a new operating system to
watch this yes
so the question was do I stay on the Intel platform
I actually bring up that point in my forensics talks
I am on an Intel platform
for my sensors
however
depending on how you want to do forensics for
example
I have done cases where I had one tax stack
where I’ve got
you know Intel Windows
Toolex
whatever
and in another platform where I’ve got
Power PC
Debian
blah blah blah blah blah and something completely different
and I will say by the way
I don't run the one system I expose in my home lab
is not an Intel system
it's a Mac Mini
and it’s running Debian on top
I tried to put on BSD I had a problem
I don’t know what that was
probably user error but
so Debian is running on that and what’s
nice about that is do you remember when the Debian
the SSL stuff when was that
that happened recently
all of the pre-compiled exploits for that
%uh and all of the pre-compiled keys
they shell code was all wrong because I was running
Power PC
and like when I did my
update or whatever I was like oh
I wonder if I’m affected by that
and it kept saying I wasn't even though I knew
I was because the
you know I had the vulnerable library version
I was like that's right this isn’t an Intel box
it's a Power PC box
so I do use that diversity argument in very very
limited situations
but it would be really expensive for me to say buy
you know eighty
I don't know I’m not even sure what I would use these days
it would be tough to find that I could get
a good price and everything
so I have to make some compromises there
but that’s not a bad idea if you have to have some kind of
like central server that was going to like watch everything maybe
you need to go that extra step to make it
even more diverse
alright so I’d like to talk just for a minute
about what I do
like to deploy
um what’s my time here
so I'm involved with this open source project called SGUIL
S-G-U-I-L
SGUIL doesn't stand for anything officially
but it originally when we first wrote it in like by the way
Bam Busher is the lead developer he’s probably actually the
only developer
the rest of us are just lamers
that's what the L means
originally it was snort GUI for lamers
%uh but then a couple people who got it
well we didn't get the joke they got a software
like I’m not a lamer I’m not going to use your software
well I don’t care if you use it or not
yeah right
But we felt okay that’s kind of
we’ll just call it SGUIL it doesn’t mean anything
So I’m going to talk to you about SGUIL but the thing about
SGUIL to remember is
it's open source it runs on
you know Picker
Distrobe Choice
or Flavor whatever you want
it's more about the data and less about the tool
so you could potentially implement this with your own tools
%uh even commercial if you wanted to
%um it’s really
about way of getting data and thinking about it and less
about the actual
the actual tool
you know this guy it’s Elvis
you know what martial art he studied
so here’s Elvis
and Elvis is the patron saint of this system
I don't know why it's been a long time
but %uh
I love Elvis because he’s in his Kenpo karate stance
and his stance is like this
which it would take him like a week to get out
of his fight stance to do anything
I actually won some concert tickets by stumping
an Elvis expert on a radio station here
in DC-
I called and said what style of martial arts did he
he’s like oh karate I’m like what style
oh I don't know
Kenpo karate well
who was his masters’ name
uh Ed Parker
and they were like oh you just won those tickets you stumped
the Elvis expert
so here you have Elvis I’m going to contrast these two methods
of doing investigations right
so you’ve got Elvis
he’s your analyst you don’t want to piss him off
he’s Elvis
he’ll hit you with his magic karate shot
he gets an alert via some system right well not these days he’s looking trim man
by the way if you’ve ever watched him in concert
he’s doing Kenpo like throughout the concert all the moves
he’s doing
he’s doing Kenpo
you zoom in he’s got a Kenpo patch on whatever
he's wearing
you look at his guitar it’s got the Kenpo patch on it
like once you’re exposed to the fact that he did this style it's
everywhere
in fact there was one
he did a concert once actually he didn't
do a concert he attended somebody's else concert
and I don't know who it was like Johnny Cash or something
but he saw him in the audience
he’s like Elvis do you want to come up here
you know do a song with me
and he’s like oh sorry you know
I'm under contract I can only perform at
this
one casino
but I’ll tell you what I’ll come on stage and do karate
so this guy is doing his performance and Elvis is just jumping on doing karate
I’ve got to find a video of that that would be great
so anyway Elvis is here
and his job is to find intruders
so he gets his console and he gets and alert
and he looks at it and he’s like
alright well
I’ve got to figure out if this matters
so what do I have to work with
well I have other alerts like a picture in front of some Cisco device
like in that range or whatever they are these days
so he creates the database and he gets more alerts
and he says well this is nice but I can’t tell if any of this matters
so that's the end of the line
right at this point he’s got two options he can either ignore it
or he can satisfy his 15 minute SOA that his customer
pays $3,000 a month
for
call the customer and say
I saw this
I don't know what it means
ball is in your court goodbye
so I don't how many of you have you had that experience with an
MSSP but that’s very very common
so to me this is
that's completely worthless so this is the
alternative I propose
so see already you can see there’s more lines so that
must be good right
so you got Elvis
he queries his data he get’s an alert he queries the
database he gets the same alert
but now the difference is he has some data to look
at
so in other words it’s no just an IDS or whatever
generate alerts
there’s some evidence to review
and the key idea behind NSM is
the evidence
is collected whether or not it has security
value
that's not quite right what I mean is you’re
always collecting data
because you don't know what is useful
in other words
if you knew what was bad
why don't you just stop it
that is the whole fallacy of security right
like
the whole thing IDS was
if you could detect it why can’t you prevent it oh yeah
right so you invent this whole IPS category
which is a silver bullet which
did really nothing
but the idea is yeah you can detect it’s bad why don’t you just
stop it well of course that makes a lot of
sense
so you have a lot of stopping bad stuff
but then there’s other bad stuff that’s happening because
you don't know it is bad right now
I mean
I learned these techniques dealing with
intruders
I’ll date myself but in 1998
intruders in China
who had written their own
virtualization platform on top of Solaris
who were doing stuff we were like holy cow
because we had no idea that they could do
that sort of thing
so there was no system that was going to detect
because we didn't even know it existed
but guess what we were keeping track of everything
that was happening
and once we knew what to look for
we checked our data like holy crap they’ve been in
here since two years ago
right this slide that I showed you here
when we started putting out these sensors there was
huge resistance
this was like
oh man we’re the air force we just defeated Iraq the
fourth biggest army in the world we kick ass
there can’t be anybody inside of our network and we’re like
please please can we put a few sensors out there and they’re
like all right but you guys are wasting your
time
so we put our sensors out and what do you think
what did we find
we were owned
everywhere
up down left right
it was terrible right we were completely owned
because nobody was watching
and then after that
boom that’s when everything took off
so the key here is that you get your alert but then you
have data to look at and the two
%uh well I should say three main forms of data you collect
we collected alerts but
we’re also
just logging all the flows we see
we call it session data but it’s just flows
and we deploy our own software to log the flows
but the key is we don't log the flows that are associated
with the alert we log
all flows
so you don’t have to know what support beforehand
you just keep track of everything
and once you know what to look for
you go look for it
I kind of liken it to the Splunk model like I
how many people have used Splunk
right Splunk is really awesome right
Splunk is the place you go when you know
what to look for
you generally don't have Splunk tell you stuff
I mean you can
but for the most part
you want to be there when you need to ask the question
and have some response
it's the same thing with this once I know what to look for
I need a place to go look
so I query my sessions and I’m like oh well look
this guy
just reached out via FTP and grabbed his tools
guess what most hackers these days still do this
right they aren’t like
STP-ing out or whatever
yeah go grab their tools over FTP
excuse me well
they grab their tools over FTP
while they’re doing that I’m logging all the packet data
and a lot of people used to say oh Bejtlich you’re
crazy who can log packet data on all their gateways
the NSA does
so guess what we can too right it’s not that tough
%uh most network connections are
DS3s or less
at least the outbound ones to the internet
so you could log a lot of packet data
I mean hard drives are cheap
they're cheap so you can grab a lot of data
yeah question what do you use to dump all the data I’ll walk
you through all of it yup yes my question is so I’m located
my servers are in Maryland
yes I’m an ISP what happens when I get stuff from
Massachusetts or California and they’re going you can’t do that
yes okay so there’s two things
the first thing I thought you were going to go down was
I’m an ISP do I do this for my
customers the answer would be no
%uh I would do this for my infrastructure
as far as the privacy stuff goes
we're we’re wrestling with ourselves and what
I end up doing is typically
scaling back to what the law will allow
and then showing that it's either adequate
or not adequate
and then I take it to the lawyers and say we have to
somehow push back against this
%uh but okay
so imagine that you do the full content though
and by the way this isn’t theoretical we do this all the time
I have a reverse engineer on my staff who
when we see machines mission going down pulling their binaries
when the machines are owned
I pass in the traffic
he pulls out the
exe
he reverses it figures out what it does
and now we go into the next stage of insert-response
so it can be done
so then we say oh shoot it uses this back door we
go back and look in the sessions and we say
oh I see this back door let's go and look at the
traffic
and it just keeps going so
the idea is that this isn’t the end of the investigation
it’s the beginning the investigation
sure
can it be done
it’s easy to do and can be done completely free
yes
yes and that is very true
everything that I’ve shown here
you could literally walk out of here
go into the FreeBSD ports tree find a SGUIL ports
do your make I mean the ports are a little ugh
I'm not
you don’t want to slam a guy who
volunteers and makes ports right
but there’s still a decent amount of work that you have
to do once the ports are installed it’s good for basically
satisfying dependencies and so forth
so this is the implementation we use as far as software stack
for %uh alert data
we use Snort
I’m starting to I’ve used Bro a little bit
I’m starting to integrate Bro though
full content data I tend to use Demon Logger
it’s Marty Rush’s implementation of Packet Logger
for session data
I use SANCP which is sort a friend of Myrobe which you can
sort of see some other options there
and then statistical data
you know think MRTGA type of thing
that
shows you traffic over time or whatever
%um and the nice thing is SGUIL is the interface to a lot
of this and you know
I’m going to show you what that looks like
by the way so this is it in a picture
so what is SGUIL well
okay yes this is a Windows screenshot
it shows that you can run your BSD back
end on the servers and then have your boss uses Windows
GUI
and log into it
and %uh
again this isn’t about the tool as much as
the data and the way you investigate it but
here’s the screenshot so
you can see we have a console here
and these are our store alerts coming in and by the way it can
be other things we've got it
this isn't a sim incidentally we were talking
just a few minutes ago like
the way we describe it is
with a sim
you could put ABCD all the way through W
into a sim
and it’d still be garbage
but with this we pick the X Y and Z that we
think give you the best value
so for us those are alert sessions and and full content
so you’ve got your interface here
and we try to present as much information
on one screen without having to do a bunch of window
management
yes it is TCL/TK
we started this back in 2001
but it works it you know it’s fine it’s platform
so here’s the packet that caused the alert
here is the of
the rule that caused the alert
and in most systems this is what you would
get
right you're left deciding if it's okay
in an HTTP transaction
for someone to have put through what looks like the
output of an ID command on Unix
where the result was
UID 0
is that good or is that bad I mean you’d probably say that sounds bad
but once you do the analysis you’ll find out it's
not the question is you have to make that decision
and every vendor that I’ve met
they leave you here
and they abandon you
they say
good luck I’ve given you the packet
like you’ll talk to the source buyer guys they’re like
I gave you the packet what more do you need
I need to know if it matters
and you’re like well
I
can give you the packet look
yeah packet so what it’s a packet
I can tell there’s a packet here yes there’s a packet and yes
it’s nice that you gave me a nice open rule so I can tell how it
came to its decision unlike you know a closed system
you can't tell
but I have to tell if this matters for me
what do you do next
we could do a couple things one thing you
can do is build transcript
the transcript is
all of the
session in this case
rendered through in this case we use TCP flow so we say
literally right-click
give me your transcript
system goes out to the sensor
pulls back the P cap data
renders it in TCP flow
colors the blue
%uh the source the red is the destination
so you can see that my system
visited the www.testmyids.com site
and it replied
with the content
so
there is no like
back door on port 80 here
this is a
by the way the other thing that’s nice is that I came
through this proxy and whatever
if I’m dealing with a binary protocol like let’s say
SNB or RPC or something that doesn’t
render well as text
that's same right-click you can instead choose to
dump it into Wireshark
so here’s the Wireshark data
and you can use anything you want to do for Wireshark
at this point
this is fast right
I don’t know how many of you have had to do this by
hand
you know you SSH out to the sensor find a pcat file
come up with a BPF in your head
you know run it
copy it someplace no this is
right-click right-click right-click I’ve got all my data
if you want to see well have I ever gone to this IP address
before
I query for my sessions and I say
you know in this case it’s a sequel query on that desk IP
and by the way you can right-click and do a default query
or else if you know what the schema looks like you can just
modify it by hand
and I think that’s it
so if you want to try any of that
like I said %uh the ports exist
I maintain some really really really
really lame scripts that automate this
but I need to install it on my home gateway or something
like that
They’re more of just a reference
but that’s what I do on BSD as far as network security
monitoring goes
I’d be happy to answer any questions
yes
what additional features are you looking for in the future I
would say for SGUIL for new features the first thing is resolve
intellectual property
because
I hired Bam as my lead incident handler at GE
so
we need to figure out
if he works on it at work
can we release it well first of all can he even work
on it at work
and secondly if he does
can we release so we're trying to work
out those I think it'll be resolved positively
because we're GE’s actually fairly pro-open-source
I told the CEO of the company that this thing
used my sequel as a back end and
he’s like I love my sequel
okay
he’s like you’ve got your money I’m like oh
okay that’s all I had to say great
%uh he hates Microsoft he hates the company
so we wanted once we get that result we want
to probably introduce other data sources
so introduce like Bro plugin
some other agents
they could accept other data
%uh we need to have
some kind of reporting mechanism
because people don't know
what comes out once you put it in
there's been some talk about making this turn
into a Splunk base application
so all the data goes into Splunk
I mean you could you'd do like use Splunk as the interface
so that's a possibility
yeah Splunk is remarkably cheap for an enterprise
app though we’ve bought like giant licenses
that have not
I mean they've been like five-figure purchases which is
really good considering how many gigabytes of data
we’re indexing
%uh but you know for the
situation here it would be an option because the free Splunk
is 500mb a day
so it's not that
any other questions
yeah I think Bro if you’ve never heard of Bro bro-ids.org
in fact I’m going to Bro training next week
in Berkeley which is just going to rock I’m so excited
about that
Bro I think is a perfect
a perfect compliment to Snort
Snort not exclusively but Snort is quite a bit about signatures
there are some few processors that look for
protocol anomalies and so forth
but Bro on it’s own is completely the opposite it’s all about
protocol anomalies
Snort has kind of like real
hackish type state keeping using flow bits
Bro is all about state
so you put the two of them together you might say
shoot I really need to know when such and such
happens
but to do that Snort I’d have to do all this
flow bits and stuff
whereas with Bro you’re like oh
just track the connections and then do this
so the two of them together I think work really
well
the questions was does Bro have Snort rule input functionality
it does to the extent that every
like hardware vendor accelerator vendor Snort competitor
says that they do
%uh Snort is the engine is always being
updated
so generally what when somebody says that
they can
%uh run Snort rules faster
they’re usually only talking about content matches
so they take whatever the the
content match is
and implement it quickly in hardware
so over time the degree to which you can map
real Snort rules fades
so whereas
five years ago it might have been like 90%
these days it's like 25%
so they probably can pull in a certain percentage
but not a lot
right right exactly so the question was about retention
of the full content data
I should mention that for alerts we try to keep for
about a year
for flows we try to keep about six months
and alerts and flows are both centralized although
given the flow volume we’re seeing we might
have to start pushing that back onto the
sensor
pcat data it is
just what we can afford as far as hard drive spaces go
my last budget
I could only spend about 2,500
to 3,000 per sensor
which limited me to about one to
yeah about one terabyte of disk space with raid
so %uh
depending on where the sensor goes that could be
three months or three weeks
or or a day or three days or three hours
right
what I do is I end up
I buy up chassis that can
potentially grow to have a lot more storage once
I have budget
I put the system out there
and I say
look this is look what I found at this location
boss
if you give me a little more more money I can put in
you know four terabytes of disk space as opposed
to one
and then they give me that
but the pcap data only stays on a sensor
so what I try to do is I have an analysis
window
and a pcap window
and I try to have that pcap window longer than
the analysis window
so the questions yes
yeah so any type of encryption on host
but the funny thing is
most of the time when I did get type of
like third-party tips
it's usually have you seen anybody visiting this IP address
and if I see the visit to that IP address
even if it’s encrypted
I know it
this isn't the whole game right
usually what I do is I use all of this identify
boxes that problems
and then I roll in to do
host-based forensics
so that some of the other coin other side
yeah that is really dependent on the way that
encryption algorithm is implemented
some of them are are very friendly to that
others are not
and others
that you know in some cases
it might be better to use another approach
like there's certain proxies that are out
there like that
Palo Alto firewall
you can specify encryption policies so
and if you go to banks if you go to certain
sites they don’t mess with the SSL
everywhere else they man it in the middle
and so you can get access to the logs that
way
so I try not to do that with the sensors so much
I try to keep it I try to make
the sensor so nobody even knows they’re there
if at all possible
yes
his comment was even if there is four
four three traffic that’s encrypted
general to be something else that isn’t
and that's really what all this is about it's
generally about getting a hint that something
is wrong
and you don't necessarily know what the hint is until
you’ve been burnt pretty badly
and then you go back and you figure out the scope
of the incident is
in no forensic case have I ever worked where I
had a complete picture
you know I had the guys hard drive I had
his logs his network traffic it's generally
you get some piece
and then you start investigating
and the reason I do this approach is because it’s cheap
you know twenty $500 commodity hardware
open source software
little bit of experience
and suddenly I’ve got some
you know some viable data
you’d think working at GE I’d have some huge
budget
no way not at all
any other questions
yes
well to tell you the truth I started using
FreeBSD specifically
%uh in 2000 and the reason was our
developers who who were building the ASM sensors
in the
they said
if we’re going to have a good network stack we should
use a BSD base stack as opposed to Linux
so that's how it started
%um since then there have been many changes in both
sides Linux within the BSDs and so forth
so I'm really not in a position to say which
is better
I I would say
I've never had a BSD let me down
put it that way
as far as FreeBSD goes specifically
there’s some like minor things that make my
life better
one is I know a lot of the network developers
so when there's an issue I can talk to them
directly
and they can say
like some of the
I don’t know who’s from the free
but some of the zero copy stuff that's being
worked on
like that helps me a lot
some it's the most stupid things like the
ability that any
any
app which
is opening up a BPF
you can track performance with the what was it
netstat -B
capital B
little things like that are helpful too
there's another question
yes
yeah so I don’t know if what you've seen in the news about
like Chinese hackers and all
this has been going on for a long time it's
just that
nowadays they're mostly on Windows but
ten years ago what was popular
like commercial in the military it was Solaris
so we were seeing all sorts weird traffic in
our Solaris boxes that we couldn’t account for
so these guys had written once we
started doing some
forensics and it wasn't the forensics of
pull the power cord which is what was popular
back then right
it was you know
let's take us the actually I think back then we were
doing
we generated a crash dump
and then analyzed it
so these guys were writing
memory resident
did not touch
did not touch the hard drive
%uh implementations where
they built their own
like hyper visor and had their own little operating
system on top of our Solaris
boxes that we couldn't see
yeah so
that was back then
right %uh
it’s I’ve worked on that side the defensive side
I’ve also worked on a not defensive side
I won’t say what that is but
%uh the stuff I saw here
that we were doing as contractors
I was I was like wow this can be done this
is really amazing so
most of the time if you have an imagination you
can sort of imagine what's happening
and if you think about it you might think well
we're not the only ones in the world who can do that
so there’s probably guys on the other
side
who can do it so then you have to start
looking for it
what you see is a progression of
things that happened at the very high end
eventually it filters down you know
really good rootkits used to be the province
of people who wrote them
but now you can buy them
find them share them whatever
sure yeah so the question is do we do any pattern analysis
there's nothing bad about Latvia
you asked a good question
but
let me put it this way
I'm creating that the first GE cert
it's 2099 but yes we just did
up our first cert
so we are we're not even like crawling yet
we’re like the baby on its back
oh look I can lift my head up
so we're still getting our hands around what does it
even mean to operate the cert data we have and
so forth
I would expect within the next two years we're going
been doing the kinds of things I would have
expected
you know a real
cert to do
it now includes things like
we know our environment so well that when we see
that box doing that that's outside the scope
it's one of those things where we have ideas
that are probably
like two years ahead of where we can implement
but once we do that
we’ll find stuff like that
have we gotten people to do their own what
so the question was I think you probably heard the question
we are actually collaborating with
%uh ICIR at Berkeley like Verne Paxon and his guys the Bro guys
and %uh at New York University so
there’s two research programs at each and
we're going to be
probably
I would guess we’re probably going to ship them data
because that’s what’s great about our method right we just
collect data so we can sign an NDA ship them data
and they can apply all their different
research
theories against it and find stuff for us
so yeah I’d expect some of that
from those guys
yes
yeah so the way I deploy is I use taps where possible
because you can’t screw it up
I mean you can there are certain fiber types you can
physically connect backwards
so just enough light will get through so the
traffic follows
but no light is reflected out to your sensor
but for the most part if you’re talking copper
done tap
it gives you your traffic
I even prefer that model for like IPS’s
if you have to use an IPS
use a bypass switch as opposed to putting it in line
I don't put anything in line because as soon as
you’re in line
what happens
you get blamed so I stay I’m like look I have a dum tap
pull the power cords it’s not going to affect the network
in the least right
I have my sensor my sensor could blow up in a ball of fire
and you wouldn’t even notice it
and all the business owners are like yes
but if I told them I’m putting this box in line
anything that happens you’re like
your box took down my ten million dollar an hour system
I’m going to kill you
so
I don't bother with that
I’ve got a good track record that’s why I’m still employed
so far
the only time I ever took something down
I was fully authorized to do
%uh we had
some script kitty
who was
defacing
web site after web site
we had some you know
Microsoft IS 4 0 websites back in the
air force
and he was dialing in getting
a new IP defacing the website
disconnecting dialing in so he had a new IP
so we had all our admins trying to block these IPs
and we’re like this isn’t working
stupid stupid defensive policies
this is all like at two o'clock in the morning
eastern time actually no central wherever I was
in Texas
and so finally I said this guy is all over the space he’s in
California he's using the UUnet
the UUnet blocker however they’re signing they’re signing
the IPs
it's just all over the place we're blocking UUnet
all of UUnet to the air force
so
I was like
execute that blocking order
yeah
I knew there was going to be hell to pay the next morning
so I the next thing I did I was I started writing
this is why I blocked this whatever and I had
tons of generals why did you I couldn’t check my email
and I got up in front of the generals and I said sir this is
why I did it I did it to protect air force assets
and all that so I was alright
yeah question
%um
yes the sensors are
scanned all the time
%uh I use them
the model I use with the sensors is you don't firewall
all things off like you might with a Windows
platform
you disabled things
I mean you traditionally you don’t turn it on
so I typically only expose SSH
the systems reach out they don’t
all the things you would think is what
I do
and of course they’re scanned
people try to brute force them of course
if I see somebody brute forcing in my sensor
who are you
because these are all internally managed
well who are you
why do you even know that this box is here
we're going to come and get you
the
sounds better than it is
we selling our fleet of black helicopters actually
we don't have a fleet of corporate jets
like a lot of other companies
we have net jets accounts
well I don’t but the CEO does we do have a helicopter I’ve seen it once
yeah the question was would
honey pot be of any value
honey pots are things that are good to run if
one you’re researcher or two you have a lot of time on your hands
because I have like a network of 300,000
honey pots
so
actually it’s more like half a million now that I think about it
so yeah at some point
there’s actually two things one is yeah at some point
you could deploy some honey pots if you see them
scanned
but I have enough systems that are
alive or getting scanned or attacked or exploited
the second thing we have is
if you're inside our network
and if you try to do anything to any any network
that is not explicitly routed by us
you end up in a sink hole
so the sink hole
is an awesome awesome place to find
misconfigured systems malicious systems and
so forth
so I have a sink hole router
and before that I had a sensor that watches that traffic
so the sink hole routers are a great
indicator
source of indicators
it also keeps a lot of load off of our firewalls
so you can’t scan Google from inside GE as
for example it goes straight into the sinkhole
I know Capitol One does that as well
that's it’s a good trick
any other questions
okay thank you very much.